Guide to the Eugene Arthur Regnier Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Eugene Arthur Regnier papers
1917-1956
MS 1409
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
(14 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, printed material, photographs, and other material documenting the personal life and professional career of Eugene A. Regnier. The primary focus of the papers is Regnier's role as an aide to Henry L. Stimson. The papers illustrate Regnier's duties in the Philippines and the State Department and highlight his publicity work and relationship with the press.
Regnier, Eugene Arthur, 1893-1956
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eugene A. Regnier's children, 1985.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1956; II. Subject Files, 1921-1955; III. Personal Papers, 1917-1956; and one accession.
Scope and Contents
The Eugene Arthur Regnier Papers consist of correspondence, writings, reports, printed material, and photographs documenting Eugene A. Regnier's personal life and professional career. Regnier, a career army officer, was a friend of Henry L. Stimson, having served as Stimson's aide during his tenure as governor-general of the Philippines, secretary of state, and secretary of war (1940-1941). While the papers document Regnier's assignments and training, they focus primarily on Regnier's duties in the Philippines and the Department of State. The papers also highlight his work in developing better relations between the Department of State and the press. The papers complement the Henry L. Stimson Papers (Manuscript Group Number 445) and include many original letters in the handwritings of both Henry L. and Mabel Stimson.
The papers, given to the Yale University Library in 1985 by Regnier's four children, are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1918-1956; II. Subject Files, 1921-1955; and III. Personal Papers, 1917-1956.
Series I is composed of personal correspondence with army friends, State Department associates, the Stimsons, and Regnier family members. Series II consists of correspondence, memoranda, records of conversations, clippings, photographs, travel memorabilia, and printed material concerning various military and diplomatic assignments and related topics. Series III includes such personal papers as financial and legal records, military orders, family photographs, and professional writings.
Series I contains correspondence with Henry L. and Mabel Stimson. These letters, which begin in 1928 and continue until a year before Mrs. Stimson's death (1955), are personal and reveal a great fondness and warmth between Regnier and the Stimsons. Many of these letters are handwritten, and copies are not located in the Stimson Papers. Various other letters concern Regnier's duties at the Department of State and the department's relations with the press. Files for George Harold Keatley, Allen Klots, John Van Antwerp MacMurray, and George Morelock contain information on these latter topics.
The series contains many notes of congratulation on appointments, marriage, and births of children; Christmas cards; and requests from friends for help in dealing with government bureaucracy. There are many family exchanges including those with Regnier's father-in-law Andrew Mcfarlane and sister Marie Louise Regnier. Letters to his wife Claire Janet Regnier date from his military service in America and in the European theater during World War II.
Series II, the largest series in the papers, is the major source of information on phases of Regnier's professional career. Folders 110-111 contain much briefing material on the Phillipine Islands. The folders refer to many of the issues that arose during Stimson's tenure as governor-general, and folders 118-20 include contemporary photographs. Topics relating to Regnier's work at the Department of State include: the London Conference of Ministers on Intergovernmental Debts in 1931; the General Disarmament Conference in Geneva in 1932; the crisis over Manchuria; and the Stimson press policy of educating members of the press corps with "background." Folders 112-113 contain briefing and organization notes for Stimson's press conferences. Regnier's military service is mainly represented by printed histories of World War II in folders 132-138. There are some mi1itary photographs in "Cavalry" files and in folder 149, reports on maneuvers and military training at Fort Bliss in folder 91, and a file on the work of the National Research Council Committee on Quartermaster Problems in folder 106. The series also includes memorabilia, photographs, and printed material about the Stimsons and their pets.
Series III consists of personal papers such as memorabilia from Regnier's military career, personal, finanical, and legal papers, military orders, family photographs, and professional writings. The series also includes obituary clippings and funeral remembrances.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Eugene A. Regnier was born in Concordia, Kansas on December 22, 1893. He was a career army officer who enlisted in June, 1917 and retired as a brigadier general in 1946. Regnier served in France during World War I, and as a liason officer with the insular government of the Philippines (1928-1929). As a liason officer with the U.S. Department of State (1929-1932), Regnier attended disarmament conferences and was assigned to the office of the secretary of state. He commanded a Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) camp (1933), served as a calvary officer (1933-1940), and then served as an aide to the U.S. Secretary of War in the Office of the Chief of Staff. Regnier also served as a combat commander in the European theater of operations (1945). He died in Carlsbad, California on December 7, 1956.
Armed Forces; Cavalry; Government publicity -- United States; Press -- United States; World War, 1939-1945; Philippines; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1929-1933; United States -- Politics and government -- 1929-1933; Photoprints; Soldiers; Regnier, Eugene Arthur, 1893-1956; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Stimson, Mabel White, 1866-1955; United States. Army; United States. Department of State; Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments ( 1932-1934 Geneva, Switzerland)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1918-1956; Series I; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by personal and corporate name.
  - A miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American veterans, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - B miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boal, Pierre de Lagarde, 1931, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - C miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carr, Wilbur John, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Cavalry School, Fort Riley, Kansas, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    General note
    See also: box 12, folders 169-170
  - Chaney, James Eugene, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conner, Fox, 1928, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    See also: box 13, folder 178
  - Crossman, Edgar G., 1929-1931, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - D miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - E miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Eastwood, Harold Eugene, 1940-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - F miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Filipino Club, Washington, D.C., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - G miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gibson, Hugh Simons, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Groome, John C., Jr., 1931, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - H miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Herr, John Knowles, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hornbeck, Stanley Kuhl, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - I miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - International Goodwill Congress, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - J miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - James, Jules, 1941, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - K miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Keatley, George Harold, 1931, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Klots, Allen Trafford, 1930-1934, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - L miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Loomis, Alfred Lee, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - M miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - McBride, Harry Alexander, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - McCloy, John Jay, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - McCoy, Frank Ross and Frances, 1930-1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mcfarlane, Andrew, 1932-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - MacMurray, John Van Antwerp, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    See also: box 2, folder 71
  - Malone, Paul Bernard, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Marshall, George Catlett, 1924, 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Merrill, Keith, 1930, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Miller, Danforth, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Moffett, William Adger, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Morlock, George Albert, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - N miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Oliver, Lunsford Errett, 1945, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - P miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Patterson, Charles H., 1931 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Patterson, Robert Porter, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    See also: box 10, folder 149
  - Patton, George Smith, Jr., 1930, 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Quezon, Manuel, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - R miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Regnier, Claire Janet (Macfarlane), 1941-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Regnier, Edward, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Regnier, Marie Louise, 1931-1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 53-54)
  - Regnier, Neomie (Madeau), 1918, 1931-1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Reynolds, Stephen C., 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Richardson, Robert Charlwood, Jr., 1919-1920, 1940-1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Robinett, Paul McDonald, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - S miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Shipley, Ruth (Bielaski), 1933-1954 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Stimson, Candace Catherine, 1929-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1928-1950 (Box 2, Folder 62-63)
  - Stimson, Mabel Wellington (White), 1929-1954 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Swift, Innis Palmer, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - T miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Taylor, Maxwell Davenport, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1948 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - U miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - W miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Walter Hines Page School of International Relations, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Wheat, George Seay, 1931-1933 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Winship, Blanton, 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Wynne, Edward Cyril, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Yale, Wesley W., 1941, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
- SUBJECT FILES, 1921-1955; Series II; 3 linear feet (8 boxes)
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Arms embargo, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Bolivia and Paraguay, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - British bases in the Western Atlantic, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Canada: military situation, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Cavalry
    - Photographs, 1942-1943, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Tactics, mechanization, associations, 1930-1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Disarmament, 1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Disarmament Conference, Geneva, 1931-1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 84-85)
  - Early, John C., 1929 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Ecole d'Application de Cavalerie, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Far East, [ca. 1926-1935] (Box 3, Folder 89-90)
    See also: box 4, folders 102-103
  - Fort Bliss, Texas, 1933-1942 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Fort Meyer, Virginia, 1930-1940 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - France, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    See also: box 3, folder 83
  - Germany, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Grandi, Dino: visit, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Hawaii: annexation, undated (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Horses
    - General, 1930-1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Photographs, 1930-1931, undated (Box 4, Folder 98)
      General
      See also: box 3, folder 81
  - Howard, William, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - London Conference of Ministers on Intergovernmental Debts, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 100-101)
  - Manchuria: Sino-Soviet and Sino-Japanese disputes, 1930-1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 102-103)
  - Mexico, 1929-1941 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - National defense, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - National Research Council: Committee on Quartermaster Problems, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Nicaragua, undated (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Passport fraud, 1930, undated (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Pet goat, dogs, 1928-1936 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Philippine Islands, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    See also: box 6, folder 116
  - Phillipine Islands, 1928-1933 (Box 5, Folder 111a-f)
  - Press conferences, 1931-1933, undated (Box 5, Folder 112-113)
  - Press policy and press relations, 1929-1933, undated (Box 6, Folder 114-115)
    See also: box 3, folder 93
  - Stimson, Henry L.
    - Biographical files, 1929-1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Pets: parrot, 1929-1940 (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Photographs: Phillipine Islands, [ca. 1927-1929] (Box 6, Folder 118-120)
    - Photographs: miscellaneous, undated (Box 7, Folder 121)
      See also: box 13, folder 172
    - Speeches
      - General, 1928-1934 (Box 7, Folder 122-124)
      - Informal discussion: Army War College, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 125)
      - "Mr. Hoover's Foreign Policy,", 1932 (Box 7, Folder 126)
        See also: box 10, folders 146-147
    - "The Pact of Paris,", 1932 (Box 7, Folder 127-128)
    - Stimson, Mabel Wellington (White), 1930-1933, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - Titanic memorial, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - U.S. Army
    - General papers, 1943-1945, undated (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - Publications
      - General, 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 132-135)
      - First U.S. Division, [1919?] (Box 9, Folder 136)
      - Fifth Armored Division, 1947, undated (Box 9, Folder 137)
      - 557th Field Artillery Battalion, undated (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - U.S. Department of State
    - General, 1931-1933, undated (Box 9, Folder 139)
    - Clippings, 1929-1934, undated (Box 9, Folder 140)
    - Organization, 1918, 1928-1931, undated (Box 9, Folder 141)
    - Press releases, 1929 October - 1933 February (Box 9, Folder 142-145)
    - Publication: Our Foreign Relations, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 146-147)
    - Speeches, 1922-1932 (Box 10, Folder 148)
  - U.S. War Department: Public Relations Division, 1942-1947, undated (Box 10, Folder 149)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1917-1956; Series III; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by record type.
  - Financial records, 1929-1949, undated (Box 11, Folder 150-151)
  - Legal papers, 1934, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 152)
  - Memorabilia
    - Postcards of Austrian military units, [1930?] (Box 11, Folder 153)
    - Regimental shoulder patches, undated (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - Miscellanea, 1919, 1934-1956, undated (Box 11, Folder 155)
  - Military orders
    - Promotions, transfers, leaves, 1919-1946, undated (Box 11, Folder 156-158)
    - Travel orders, 1940-1941 (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Biographical, 1929-1953, undated (Box 11, Folder 160)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931-1934 (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Passport, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 162)
  - Photographs
    - Personal and family, [1936?] - 1945 (Box 12, Folder 163-164)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12, Folder 165)
  - Writings
    - Articles
      - "Communism and Common Sense,", [1930?], 1933 (Box 12, Folder 166)
      - "The Government and the Press,", 1933 (Box 12, Folder 167)
      - "Isolation,", undated (Box 12, Folder 168)
    - Lectures: Cavalry School, Fort Riley, Kansas, 1939-1940 (Box 12, Folder 169-170)
    - Notebook: "Army Officer's Notebook,", undated (Box 12, Folder 171)
- OVERSIZE
  - Stimson, Henry L.: photographs: miscellaneous, undated (Box 13, Folder 172)
  - U.S. Army: publications: 628th Tank Destroyer Battalion, undated (Box 13, Folder 173)
  - Memorabilia
    - Diplomas, certificates, commissions, 1917-1945 (Box 13, Folder 174)
    - Maps, 1932, 1943-1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 175)
    - Poster, in German and French, from Luxembourg, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 176)
  - Photographs
    - Personal and family, undated (Box 13, Folder 177)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 13, Folder 178)
- Additional material, 1945; Accession 2007-M-095
  - Action Against the Enemy, Report No. 9, Combat Command Fifth Division, U.S. Army [photostat copy], 1945 April (Box 1)